so you open your charts and you're about
to Mark some structure but then you get
hit with all the doubts do I take from
this low to this high or is it this low
to this High well what about that low
what about this what about this but wait
a second is the market actually bearish
here so is the direction bullish or
bearish how do I actually draw my FIP is
it from here to here or is it from here
to here or are we actually bearish right
now like what exactly do I draw if you
have this type of confusion in this
video we're going to destroy all your
doubts about Market
structure all right in today's lesson
I'm going to teach you about systematic
Market structure mapping and we're going
to do this by introducing you to the
concept of the valid ranges now this is
a concept that I came up with after four
to six months of testing and really
asking the very simple question what
makes structure valid and how I can
systemize it and then the valid ranges
were born so what are valid ranges those
are specific rules for determining your
valid structural formations and those
formations are simply our higher highs
higher lows lower lows and lower highs
now disclaimer if you are a complete
beginner if you don't know what even
Market structure is I'm going to leave a
link in the description or leave a card
that you can click go and watch a very
strong foundational video so you know
what Market structure is and then if you
have the question all right how do I
Mark Val higher lows or lower highs you
come back at this video now why do we
need valid ranges well firstly to ensure
that we draw structure correctly and
also flow with the most recent structure
shifts because a lot of times you take
those very massive large legs and then
the market has already shifted 10 times
before you actually know it to also
ensure that we always have the same
Market structure markups and remain
systematic with our analysis because
you're always if you're always drawing
structure in a different way well you
don't have an edge in order for you to
achieve consistency your analysis also
has to be consistent and the valid
ranges are going to help you with that
and finally as a result this is going to
remove any doubt and confusion when it
comes to picking your major higher lows
and lower highs because just the rules
are rules you cannot go around them so
you might ask what are the main aspects
of a valid range we're going to cover
all of these but they simply consists of
two things
having an opposite candle so that is a
candle that closes in the opposite
direction of the current Trend so if
we're having bullish push we need a
bearish candle if we're having a bearish
push we're going to need a bullish
candle quite simple and also having a
pullback candle so that is a candle that
does not break the previous candle high
or the previous candle low and of course
this variable for the pullback candles
it can be tweaked based on the time
frames or based on your requirements so
once you actually learn those rules feel
free to change them feel free to tweak
them to your
liking now before we get into the
details I just want to very quickly
cover the candle Anatomy so what does a
Candlestick actually consist
of we are having open high low and close
ohlc values okay so in the in the case
of a bullish candle the market is going
to open where the body starts okay the
lower Wick is going to be the candle's
low then the market pushes up it reaches
a high and then it retraces and where it
closes this is where the body is going
to end okay so that is very basic stuff
but I just want to cover it for a
bearish body the market actually opens
here this is where it opens it first
pushes up to make a high then it very
nicely pushes down all the way down to
make a candle low retraces and closes so
the body is your open and close and the
Wicks are your candle high and candle
low okay okay so very simple hopefully
that's clear now with that being said
let's talk about the first aspect of the
valid ranges and that is the opposite
candles so what is an opposite candle
pretty simple this is a candle in the
opposite direction of the current Trend
or the current range so simply that is a
bearish candle in the bullish Trend or a
bullish candle in the bearish trend now
why do we need an opposite candle
because an opposite candle signifies
that there is a real pullback and at the
opposite side of the market is entering
also how I actually discover this is by
going to the line chart you know on
trading view you have your candlesticks
but you also have a line chart and if
you ask the question when does a line
chart actually makes a
pullback when there is an opposite
candle okay so when there is when the
market is pushing up so if I just very
quickly give you an example when you
have a line chart let's say that the
market is pushing up okay so when it's
actually going to push down when we have
an opposite candle so if those candles
are bullish bullish bullish bullish when
you have a bearish candle close that is
when the line chart actually makes a
pullback okay so that is pretty much how
that came up to be
now the important part here is once
again the candle closure it must be an
opposite battery and by now you pretty
much know the candle Anatomy a candle
closure you we have the open and the
close and that should be pretty much
opposite to the trends that we currently
have so when comes to Wix when it comes
to looking at the opposite candle for
the valid range Theory the Wix or the
type of Candlestick like what exactly
how does it look like it does not matter
what truly matters is to be of an
opposite color which also means that
dois don't count it must be either a
bearish candle in a bullish Market or a
bullish candle in a bearish market let
me give you some examples here it is
quite simple we are having an overall
bullish Trend here so bullish candle
bullish candle again the Wicks don't
really matter what matters here is that
again we have a push and right now we're
having an opposite candle what
classifies this as an opposite candle
well very simply a bearish
body all right in a bearish trend
bearish candle bearish candle whoop
There is a very nice bullish candle that
is our opposite candle okay super simple
that's it and that's the first thing you
need for a valid range and it's
extremely simple hopefully it makes
sense now let's give some chart examples
let's plot a chart here and I want you
to pause the video and try to spot all
the opposite candles this is an overall
downtrend so pause the video and spot
the opposite
candles did you pause you
nasty all right I hope you did so let's
pull them out there we go so I actually
took only the most important opposite
candles that we need so here we see we
have a very nice push lower bearish
bearish bearish candles and all of a
sudden we're having a bullish candle
okay so precisely in this situation here
this is when the line chart is actually
starting to make a pullback so that's an
opposite candle this and this and this
are all opposite candles this and this
and this are also opposite candles but
what we truly need is just one opposite
candle we haven't really gotten to the
rules but only in this case this matters
then again you can see the market
actually breaks this valid range and
what it does here immediately after
forming a new low opposite candle
continues to break opposite candle in
fact to break structure again bearish
bearish bearish bearish the first
opposite candle there it is so that is
the first rule that is the first thing
we need for a valid range and then again
you can see the market creates a
thousand more opposite candles it makes
a very big pullback and then as soon as
we pretty much break this low so again
we haven't really gotten to the rules
bearish bearish bearish candle Boop all
of a sudden up opposite candle perfect
right then we break structure again
bearish bearish bearish all right there
is the first opposite candle Bingo right
that's it very simple let me give you
one more example are you going to pause
the video this time you already saw how
I did the example so right now pause it
and do it
yourself damn if you didn't pause this
time I'm going to find you and you know
what I'm going to do all right let's put
them on so there are pretty much the
most most important opposite candles
here we're having a very nice push
higher the market creates the first
opposite candle Bingo that's what we
need the market then pulls back again
with couple more opposite candles
pullback candles then we break structure
again so one two bullish candles
opposite candle we break structure again
opposite candle so in this case here
those two things are valid ranges those
two things here you can actually trade
and that's amazing we push up once again
breaking structure bullish candle
bullish candle all right bearish candle
opposite the market breaks again bullish
bullish all right opposite bullish once
again opposite okay then we continue to
push lower but we don't actually
continue higher this time we actually
end up breaking the valid range that
caused the last structure break okay and
then we break it and you can see
immediately on the break we immediately
print an opposite candle the market
continues lower opposite candle
continues lower and here we pretty much
got the opposite candle but in the same
time we also made the trend change
because this here is a valid range
bullish bullish bullish bullish all
right bearish all right then we push up
again two bullish one bearish opposite
candle then we make a very nice series
of bearish candles and then the first
bullish one is our opposite candle okay
so hopefully with those two little
examples it makes sense if not leave a
comment we're going to tackle it now on
to the next part the pullback candles
Theory now I want you to really pay
attention because this one is going to
be a little bit more complicated than
the opposite candles so what are
pullback candles well it is a candle
that does not break the previous
candle's high or the previous candle's
low depending on the Direction all right
so if you are in a bullish Market a
pullback candle should not break the
previous candle High because we're going
up right and if you're in a bearish
market the current candle should not
break the previous candle's low because
we're going down okay now what does the
pullback candle actually signify because
we always want to be looking at the why
so why are those things actually
important well it signifies that there
is no continuous buying or selling
pressure and that the market is actually
pulling
back okay so here you need remember that
in the opposite candles all we cared
about is the body so is it bullish or
bearish body here the important part are
the wicks so we're going to be looking
at the Wicks of the candles which is why
once again you really have to learn
candle anatomy and you have to start
looking at the open high low and close
values of the candles on trading view
because the high and low stats are going
to be important in order to truly
determine pullback Candles now again I
said it but I'm going to say it again
the color of the candle when it comes to
being a pullback candle does not matter
only the wick matters when it comes to
looking for a pullback candle okay and
so pretty much much the pullback
candle's higher low is compared with the
highest or lowest candle in the current
range now that might sound a little bit
confusing we're going to look into the
details but pretty much when the market
pushes up and up and up and then pretty
much a pullback will be a candle that
does not break the last high in this
case but of course examples are
incoming now let's have a look at some
examples oh yeah so I just wanted to
mention here uh when if you trade
trigger this on trading view you are
going to have a look at these uh things
so this is your open high low and close
those are the precise price points of a
any specific candle and I'm going to
show you later how to actually look at
those now onto some
examples so here is the first example of
pullback candles so again you can see
we're pushing up we're pushing up and
then we right now look at the Wicks so
this here was the previous candle's high
and you can see then the next candle the
high of the next candle does not break
the previous candle's High okay so in
this case this is a pullback candle
because it does not break the previous
candle's high at the same time this is
also an opposite candle because it also
has a bearish body so this here by
itself by the way is already a valid
range this is already a valid pullback
okay here is uh bearish bearish all
right there is the lowest low right now
in terms of this bearish push okay the
market makes a pullback but again we
don't look at the body in this case we
look at the wick does the wick cross the
previous candle's low no all right so
this candle here is a valid pullback
candle that's it it's also quite simple
you just have to see it a couple of
times in order to really make sense of
it let me give you some more okay
bullish situation bullish candle okay
and then we have a pullback candle here
now why is this candle a pullback candle
well because it didn't cross the
previous candle's High okay and this
pullback candle's high is actually lower
than the previous candle's high that
makes it a pullback candle okay now here
I give you an example where the body is
actually
bullish okay so this is not an opposite
candle when it comes to the bullish push
but it's actually a pullback candle
because it does not break that highest
high here if for example just very
quickly to give you a little example to
illustrate my point if let's say this
candle here went to break this high
would this be a pullback candle right
now no because that high was crossed so
this is not a pullback candle then this
candle is going to have a new high and
we have to wait for the new candle to
open and see is it going to cross it or
is it not going to cross it okay but of
course more details on that a little bit
later and of course we have the exact
same bearish example bearish candle
bearish candle there is the last
candle's low so this is in this case the
lowest low that we have the next candle
opens it does not cross that previous
candle's low so in this case we mark
this one as a pullback candle but you
can see in this case it is not an
opposite candle why because it does not
have a bullish body okay so kind of you
can see that there are two situations
here this candle in this case is both a
pullback candle and an opposite candle
but in this situation
this candle is a pullback candle but
it's not an opposite
one let's have a look at some more
examples this is exactly the one that I
gave you so here is for example um not
valid pullback candles so here is for
example the push the push same example
as last time I actually even gave an
example of this one there is that
previous candles high but you can see
the market then prints on opposite
candle however remember when it comes to
pullback candles we look mainly at the
wicks so the wicks in this case the wick
went above that previous candle's high
and wicked it so this here this candle
is not a pullback candle it is an
opposite candle because when it comes to
opposite candles we only look at the
body but it's not a pullback candle so
then the next candle what the next
candle should not do it it should not
cross that current candle's high right
there is the bearish example bearish
push bearish push there was the last
candle's low but then the Market opens
again and it crosses that candle's low
okay so this here in this case is an
opposite candle so we have made the
bullish body the line chart is already
starting a pullback however the market
is not yet in pullback mode because it
hasn't made a pullback candle that does
not break that latest candle's low so in
this case once again we're going to
refer in when the next candle opens
we're going to refer to the low of this
candle and we should not see that next
candle that opens break below this
low
okay hopefully that's clear because
right now we're getting to the rules and
I'm sure we're going to get to some more
examples then you're going to watch the
rules again and then all you need to do
is just go on the charts
okay the main variable are the pullback
candles so when it comes to the rules
you can decide to use one pullback
candle so PBC by the way is short for a
pullback candle so you can decide to use
one pullback candle on the 50-minute
time frame or maybe then even two
pullback candles on the fly in the daily
time frame or you can decide to use two
pullback candles on the 50 minute and
one pullback candle on the 4 and on the
daily for Simplicity right now for for
this lesson let's stick to one pullback
candle and also one opposite candle for
the opposite candles I would say all you
need is one because as I said all we
need is that line chart to actually make
a pullback and it does the pullback when
there is just one opposite candle so
again keep it simple you do not need two
opposite candles you don't need three
opposite candles for a valid range all
you need is one opposite candle then
what matters later is that you actually
focus on finding the pullback candle
okay now the next very important rule is
that a valid range always always causes
a structure break SB or a trend change
TC now if you don't know how that stuff
work again I'm linking you back back to
that YouTube video that I mentioned
earlier and I'm also going to invite you
to our The Fanatic Foundation module
which is in school where I teach all of
that stuff also in great detail you can
find links in the description okay so
always needs to break structure and
always needs to make either a structure
break or a trend
change now for Simplicity in this lesson
we're also going to be utilizing Wicks
as breaks because Wicks are a lot easier
to track especially while you learn
right now the valid ranges
later on when you master the valid
ranges with Wix you can very easily
shift to body braks uh however body
braks sometimes because become a little
bit complicated because you might get
for example a valid range that is being
Wicked out five times but not really
body broken and then uh the market
starts actually changing in the opposite
direction but you're still actually
looking for that body break okay I have
back tested this thoroughly wix's brakes
Works amazing what truly matters in this
case is that you have a good price
positioning on the higher time frames
but I'm already speaking for entries
okay and now when it comes to Weck and
body breaks we're going to cover in
another video about fake outs and
breakouts and I'm also going to link
another potential video where I actually
talk about this as well
okay now the process all you need is to
get your rules ticked so all you need
once again is one pullback candle and
one opposite candle that's it now the
order at which the order at which they
actually arrive can vary so sometimes
the opposite candle can appear first
then other times the pullback candle can
appear first then you have to wait for
an opposite candle once again all you
need to do is just master that candle
anatomy and just wait for that valid one
pullback candle or that valid one
opposite candle okay and other times for
example one candle can fulfill both
variables one candle can be both an
opposite candle and a pullback candle
simultaneously which is amazing you
immediately have a valid range okay so
the aim here is to become a master of
candle anatomy and really looking at the
candles and reading them on a candle by
candle basis tracking the candles until
you pretty much fulfill the rules okay
now before we jump into some examples
some details always use the Open high
and low close values when in doubt for
the pullback candles because equal highs
and equal lows so perfectly equal highs
and lows are not pullback candles and
one pip difference actually is a
pullback candle so if we ever get like
two Wicks that are very close to each
other check the the highs of those Wicks
if they're equals it's not a pullback
candle okay a very important thing to do
also is to use the highlighter tool on
trading view I'm going to show you how
to mark your valid ranges because I've
taught this valid ranges to to a lot of
people and there is one one big mistake
that is being done especially in the
beginning is that Traders tends to draw
internal structure okay and what I mean
by this is I'm immediately going to give
you an example just to stick it in your
head you're having um let's say you're
having this valid range break and then
you're trading from this high to this
low because at this low you get an
opposite candle and you get a pullback
candle but then what happens is the
market starts doing like that and so
what Traders tend to do is they say okay
stru stru break structure break Trend
change Trend change structure break this
is wrong we're trading between this High
to this low that is our valid range
anything inside does not matter okay so
just giving you that a little bit of a
kind of a tip here we're of course going
to look at it on the charts but just to
kind of you know just give it to it
right now so you start thinking about it
any price move ment as I said inside of
a valid range is internal only the major
High and the major low matter so I'm
going to show you how to mark your major
highs and lows with the highlighter
to when you learn and master both the
opposite candles and the pullback
candles then you can very easily change
your valid range preferences so what for
example I used to do is sometimes on the
50 minute instead of a one pullback
candle I start using two pullback
candles because the markets are choppy
and I want to increase the probability
of my valid range or you can use for
example One pullback Candle on the 50
minute and two pullback candles on the 4
hourly time frame and then one pullback
candle on The Daily once you master how
to use that strategy you can pretty much
tweak it to your own liking and you can
start testing what works on every single
time
frame mastering also the valid ranges
will immediately make your supply and
demand zones easier because there is a
supply and demand Zone within every
valid range but of course more on that
we're going to cover in another lesson
so let let me right now give you some
textbook examples of a valid range again
textbook in the form of um just textbook
examples here is for example a 50 minute
valid range scenario where I using one
opposite candle and one pullback candle
as my valid range criteria okay candle
up candle up okay then we have an
opposite candle which is also a pullback
candle why is that well because we're
having a bearish body perfect rule one
is thick this was the high and then the
next candle's high does not cross that
candle's high so this is also a pullback
candle check this here is a valid range
the market pulls back then this High
becomes our valid Range High and when
the market breaks it perfect okay then
of course we ask what is the valid range
that caused the break of this high it's
immediately this one because this was
already a valid range okay here is
another example bullish bullish all
right opposite candle check but is it a
pullback candle no why well because it
crossed the previous candle's High okay
so then what we wait for well we have an
opposite candle we need a pullback
candle and so then we take this as our
reference point and you can see the next
candle is a bullish candle but we don't
care right now about the body we care
that the market actually does not break
Above This candle's high does this
candle break no so that is our pullback
candle with the opposite candle this
pullback is a valid range and this is
our valid range low the Market breaks
perfect okay
here the market pushes up it pushes up
and what are we having here we're having
an opposite candle but is it a pullback
candle it's not because those two Wicks
are perfectly equal and as I told you in
this case you have to really look at the
High stats because if they're perfectly
equal then this candle here is not a
pullback candle however we already have
an opposite candle which is good okay so
opposite candle there is one pullback
candle that does not break that previous
candle's High perfect that is a valid
range pullback the market breaks there
is the low that caused the break here's
another example here pushing up pushing
up what is this that is a pullback
candle okay rule one is checked we have
a pullback candle but is it an opposite
candle no it's not and then the next
candle is actually the opposite candle
which is also a pullback candle okay and
then the market continues to break
perfect that is a valid range okay so
those are the textbook examples when it
comes to the one opposite candle and one
pullback candle so right now let me give
you an example when it comes to two just
to show you how it actually looks like
so in that case we're drawing four
hourly valid ranges in which we're using
a one opposite candle and two pullback
candles pushing up pushing up making a
high okay so there is an opposite candle
that is also a pullback candle so then
in this case we need two pullback
candles so we always are going to
reference so this is a very important
point we're always going to reference to
this high that is our highest high that
is the high of the range so the market
should not break Above This High okay if
we want to have a pullback candle and
then we can see here this is an opposite
candle which is also a pullback candle
because it does not break this High the
next candle is also a pullback candle
not an opposite but we don't care about
the opposite anymore because we already
got it it's a pullback candle because it
does not break that high if it breaks
this High here it's cool but it should
not break that high so then this
pullback is a valid range with two
pullback
candles pushing up pushing up we're
getting an opposite candle but it's not
a pullback candle so then we anchor to
this high and then we get one pullback
candle that does not break this High two
pullback candles that do not break this
High perfect right that here is a valid
range pushing up pushing up equal highs
so this is an opposite candle but it's
not a pullback candles then we need one
two pullback candles to then break the
high this pullback here is a valid range
okay push push pullback candle but not
an opposite and then we get the opposite
which is also pullback candle break
perfect okay those are your textbook
scenarios when it comes to both one and
two pullback candles right now just for
your reference let me show you some
invalid range
so you know what you're looking
for bullish bullish all right we're
having an opposite candle here cool but
then we always refer to that previous
candles high in this case this High got
taken okay then this High got taken okay
so we got an opposite candle but then
this one broke okay so right now
actually the sequence
resets and then again we see okay the
market continues to push then again we
get that opposite candle but it's still
not a pullback candle so here we first
got the
OC but the market didn't make a PBC and
it actually broke the OC okay so then we
reset the sequence and we're like okay
so we have a new high and that is not an
opposite candle it's not also a pullback
candles then we actually get the
pullback candle okay so rule one is
checked what do we need next is we need
a pullback candle to uh to not break
this
High all right so then here in the next
example we're having bullish bullish
then we have an opposite candle here but
it's not a pullback candle because it
broke that previous candle's high and
then we get these equals so this here is
not a pullback candle because we have
equals then you can see the market just
keeps breaking higher and higher and
higher so when you have a break of the
previous candle High you have to reset
that sequence of opposite candle and
pullback candle once again all right so
here for example we have an opposite
candle but then the next candle breaks
okay so right now we need a new opposite
candle so now we have this candle okay
so right now we have an opposite candle
but we still need a new pullback candle
and then if the next candle two breaks
well again we keep waiting for new
opposite candle and for new pullback
candle we need to have that pullback we
need to have these candles that are
actually not breaking above or below the
previous candles high and
low now you're also going to encounter
situations that I call Wicks and
those are very candles that take out
both the high and the low so in that
case we can see we have a push a push
there we have an opposite candle but
it's not a pullback candle because it
breaks the previous candle's high and
then we have a beautiful pullback candle
here good this is a valid range already
that is a valid High okay and then here
you can see the candle opens it takes
the high and it also takes the low of
the valid range so that is that
Wick usually happens during news usually
happens during volatile times so then
you simply have to wait and keep
following the rules again now when this
candle closed that was an opposite
candle so what do we need we need a
pullback candle there's the pullback
candle and there is the market breaking
the high okay so this right now actually
turns into a valid range we just keep
following the rules okay so when you get
that Wick always wait a little bit
so if I show you a little bit another
example how it can play it out push push
opposite candle but not pullback candle
then there is the pullback candle and
then the market breaks the low but at
the same time breaks the high okay so
this is actually a structure break here
but you just have to wait a little bit
to see if there is actually going to be
a new valid range formed and then you
simply apply the rules okay so here is
that high of that Wick the market
makes both an opposite candle and a
pullback candle so right now this turns
into a valid Range High that when is
broken we're going to find the valid
range low and right now we have our
structure okay so hopefully that makes
sense you probably have to rewatch this
again and again right now I'm going to
go on the charts and give you a lot of
examples so that you can actually start
training your eyes and then of course
you are going to start practicing on
your own so let's go on the
charts all right here we are on the
charts and right now it's time for some
chart Works two things you have to do
the first thing is to go right here on
that little button and find the
highlighter too and make it to favorite
so that you can actually have a very
easy access to it okay and then of
course uh you can just pick your colors
uh from here right I just picked this
blue with low opacity but again just
feel free to play with this one I'm
going to not going to give a tutorial on
trading view I have a tutorial on that
and then of course you're going to need
the arrows that I have also made a
tutorial on so depending on the time
frames that you're using I have like
flly up and down daily up and down 50
minute up and down down 30 minutes 5
minutes 1 minute and 1 minute TC if you
want a full tutorial on all of this link
down in the description for my free
trading Fanatics Community where I give
you a full tutorial on how to do all of
this uh because it looks pretty good and
it also links to all the time frames now
we open this chart and we want to start
marking up our valid ranges so the keys
for valid ranges is to not be so zoomed
in but also not be so zoomed out like
you don't need your charts to look like
that but you also don't want your charts
to look like this because often times
you can also miss some valid ranges now
in that case let's I usually start from
a little bit to the left just to once
again ensure that I'm not trading in
some sort of internal structure okay the
latest valid range I see is exactly so
if I take the right two is exactly right
here okay so why is that a valid range
you might T well we have the market
pushing pushing pushing pushing we have
that high and then the market makes what
is this an opposite candle which is also
a pullback candle all right so this
right here is a valid range already and
it makes a valid Range High then the
market proceeds to break it okay and
then immediately upon the break I ask
the very important question what is the
valid range that caused the break and a
valid range is simply again looking at
the rules there is the valid range we
wouldn't have had a valid Range High and
right uh if we didn't have right now a
valid range low so then what I do is I
mark this as my higher low and then I
what I simply have to do is wait for a
new valid Range High to form in this
case you can see the market pushes up it
prints an opposite candle but is this
opposite candle a pullback candle no why
because you can see the market actually
crosses that previous candle's high so
this is not a pullback candle but it's
an opposite candle so also how I
actually teach this in in the school
Community is if you you just Mark right
so this is an OC okay but if you want to
practice but not a PVC okay so then what
you take is you take that highest candle
and you refer it to the next one so what
is this candle that is not an opposite
candle because we're stillo bullish but
it's a pullback candle okay so guess
what right now you have your valid Range
High and why is this a valid Range High
because it's an opposite candle and then
next to it we have a pullback candle and
again right now we're using the rule of
one pullback candle and one opposite
candle so we have a valid Range High
right now and we have a valid range low
there we go your first valid range then
what the market does it actually breaks
this valid range low and what does that
give us that give us the trend change
because we were bullish and right now
we're bearish right now what are we
waiting for we're waiting for a valid
range low to form what do we need one
opposite candle and one pullback candle
bearish bearish bullish all right
beautiful bullish candle so there is our
OC so opposite candle is this opposite
candle also a pullback candle not really
why because it broke the previous
candle's low so candle Anatomy says that
this is not a pullback candle then what
the next candle does it continues on
actually and keeps breaking further so
right now we have a brand new low and
the market has printed one more bearish
candle so in this case we have to reset
the sequence because we have again a new
low here the market still pushed bearish
that's the new low and then what do we
have we're having a pullback candle
which is also an opposite candle so here
in this case we have OC plus PBC and
guess what in this case if we're using
one pullback candle Ru in this case we
this defines this as our valid range low
and we mark it like that with this Dash
to okay with this highlighter tool sorry
you mark it like that and right now what
is the valid Range High you already have
it right
here right you already have it right
here this is what caused the market to
break lower right now you have a valid
low from a valid high and if you want to
draw your PD range there it is Market
pulls back to the 50% and then goes on
to break this structure low what do we
need right now bearish bearish bearish
all right so firstly what after this
break we ask the question what is the
valid high that caused the break of the
valid low or in this case it's quite
easy it's this one is this pullback a
valid range or yes it is right so from
this low we have a pullback candle and
an opposite pullback candle pullback
candle this is also pullback candle
based on that and then we break and
usually it's going to be pretty much the
highest point in that case Okay so right
now this is live conditions what are we
going to need we're going to need an
opposite candle and a pullback candle
but we're going to get that in 11 hours
what are we currently getting so so far
is both things the market hasn't broken
this low so that is currently a pullback
candle okay and it's also bullish in a
bearish market so that is also an
opposite candle okay and if you then
just do to the go to the left you just
keep start doing this there is another
break of structure now is this a valid
Range High well yes it is why because
again it made this high this is the
highest high and then the next candle is
both an opposite candle and a pullback
candle that does not break this High the
market pulls back makes this low pushes
up then what is the low that caused the
break of the high there it is okay same
thing here we're having that high that
is broken okay so why is this High a
valid range because I probably should do
it like that okay so let's uh this is
how you can also practice so let let's
take a look at this price action here
real quick now the first thing we have
to do is really get clear on where
actually the real valid range is because
what a lot of people do is they just
jump on the chart like that and say okay
we have a structure break here and then
we have a structure break here but is
that really valid let's zoom in a little
bit is this here a valid range no it's
not why because we're having this candle
High okay good then we're having a
pullback candle good but do we have an
opposite candle no so this is not a
valid range we track it a little bit
further okay look at here is this a
valid range well uh yes it is we're
having this High then we're having an
opposite candle which is also a pullback
candle and then we also have another
pullback candle and then the market
breaks okay so then of course okay there
is a break here so what actually caused
that break in this case we have to mark
uh this low here because that is
actually it's a little bit tricky here
but that is the low that caused the
break of the
high okay and then you can see from this
low all the way to this High which is
where we actually had a valid Range High
form now why is this a valid Range High
because it has again bullish candle then
on the next candle we're having an
opposite candle which is also a pullback
candle that does not break that previous
candle's high so what you can see in
this case is that actually our range was
this it's not all the way down from here
okay although you can probably take it
like this it's this that is very recent
Market structure and then what you can
see happening is this is exactly where
we made the trend change so up until
this point we were bullish but we
started seeing signs that the market
doesn't really want to hold this is
where potentially orderflow comes in all
right and then the market makes a trend
change then you simply ask the question
okay what is the last valid range that
caused this trend change you track it
back okay is this a valid range yes it
is okay and then simply then the valid
Range High that caused the break is this
guy
here and then you can see here we form
this low and then what do we do here we
form a up opposite candle which is also
a pullback candle so guess what taking
it into the one pullback candle rule
this is also a structure break because
this here was a valid lower low why well
because it has again next to it an
opposite candle and a pullback candle
the next candle breaks it so then as we
break you ask the question okay well
what is the high that caused the break
of the low it's this one and then in
that case in the next candle we're
having immediately the next Trend change
and you can see how nicely your flowing
right now so right now we're having this
very nice push what are we waiting for
we're waiting for a pullback candle and
an opposite candle that's it we keep
pressing is that something no this one
just keeps pushing okay good there we go
we had the high and then right now on
the next candle we have both an opposite
candle which is also a pullback candle
so we mark this high right now and
anything inside between this low which
is the low that actually caused the
trend change here between this low and
this high is in
etal that is our premium discount range
and then what you simply wait is either
for the market to break above that major
high or to break below that major low
for a trend change Market Dives below
the 50% and expands okay and this is
exactly where you once again mark up
your structure break and you ask the
very simple question okay what is the
the valid range LW that caused the break
well in that case again quite simple
it's that
low all right pushes up right now what
are we looking for where we have a high
we need a pullback candle and an
opposite candle there we go both a
pullback candle and an opposite candle
so in this case this here is a valid
high and this here is a valid range the
market pulls back okay breaks above okay
we have another structure break and then
we're getting to where we were actually
okay this is a high high high right now
so we wait for it to actually make a
valid Range High keeps pushing keeps
pushing there it is push push push
opposite candle which is also a pullback
candle as it does not break that
previous candle's high this is a valid
Range High and also we forgot to mark
the high lows here that broke this we
drop our PD range okay and then
potentially wait for a 50% pullback if
it comes in and uh then you just
continue the process but in this case
the market just continues to break and
then we got the trend change okay now
this applies to every single time frame
now the lower you go the trickier it
will potentially get but for example
right now I can just quickly go to the
50 minute time frame and immediately
start marking valid ranges and this is
where it could potentially get a little
bit tricky because you really have to
look at the details okay so again I'm
just going to zoom out a little bit just
to ensure that there is nothing internal
okay well I see that there is nothing
internal and I'm going to potentially
Start From Here There is this structure
break on the 50 minute what caused that
break it is this High okay okay this
High to this low why is this a valid low
because it had an opposite candle and
then it had a pullback candle so here we
have a new structure break okay what
caused that structure break it was that
high and then you can see on the next
candles the market actually makes a
trend change okay and then we have a new
low what are we looking for right now
we're looking for a new high and if you
zoom in here what you can see is that if
I actually just do it like that to make
it easier okay we're having new trend
change what do we need right now is we
need the new valid Range
High what is this that's a pullback
candle check do we have a uh sorry this
is an opposite candle check do we have a
pullback candle not yet so we have to
wait so the next candle should not break
Above This candle's
high does this break yes okay so right
now we have to wait once again for an
opposite candle and a pullback
candle what is this this is an opposite
candle but is it a pullback candle well
here we check that High stats I just go
on the on the uh candle itself and I
look at here at the H so the H here is
272 and I go to the next candle 272 this
is not a pullback candle that is just an
opposite candle so right now I want to
see the next candle to not break Above
This high and it does not break Above
This high so in that case this here
turns into a valid range that could
potentially get
broken there is the break and then you
simply ask okay so what is then the low
that caused the break well it's usually
going to be the lowest point if there is
not some sort of a valid range here
which we don't really get all right so
that is the low we break up right now we
wait for a new high which we immediately
get there is that high okay that's that
high we're having immediately a pullback
candle and an opposite candle so right
now our overall range is this so now we
wait again Market pulls
back okay consolid so you can see here
you can start making the mistake right
remember this is why you always Mark so
I would even remove all of these and I
want you to keep only the most recent
ones there it is this is what we're
having right now from this low to this
High anything inside is internal because
right now we can start making oh break
of structure lower oh Trend change
higher no this is internal right now
the trend is still
bullish and there is exactly where we
actually make the trend change is then
asked the question okay what is the
valid range that caused that Trend
change you track it back there it is the
last pullback and is this pullback a
valid range yes it is there is the
market pushing lower opposite candle and
a pullback candle and then continues to
break so then you mark this as your high
okay and then you pretty much all you
need right now is just this you have the
Trend change from this high and right
now what are we looking for we're
looking for a lower low to form there is
the lower low we're having a low and
we're having an opposite candle which is
also a pullback candle
okay we also have to mark it up don't
forget and here we're entering during
Asia which is when usually the market
gets a little bit choppy here is another
break of structure with a wick what is
the valid range that cause that break we
track it back it is this guy right now
again we're trading from this high to to
this low and that low is already
established because it has here in a
bearish market opposite candle good and
then the next candle is a pullback
candle so pretty much this low is
valid and then yeah we actually get the
okay so this is some Asian news we're
having
this I was going to make a mistake we're
having this trend change because from
this high to this low this is what the
range we're having this trend change and
here is the detail okay in that case
what is the valid range that caused that
break well it's not this low it's
actually this low and why is this low
because here we having again if you
imagine that here we want to see a
bearish range that pushes higher we have
that high which is an opposite candle
and then we have this is a pullback
candle so this by itself here if you
just take isolate this little thing that
is a valid range that causes the break
okay
but this is the actual one that actually
got broken
okay so here you can see we had a
pullback candle but it's not an opposite
candle so we still keep looking for the
rules there it is this right now is a
established as a valid high high why
because it has a high and then next to
the next candle the next candle has an
opposite candle and the pullback
candle Market pulls
back and then it breaks the major high
once again and then here is again that
other detail is you have to ask okay
what is the valid range that caused the
break in this case you have two options
it's the lowest low or it's that low now
why is it this low is because this here
by itself is also a valid range this is
where you have to learn how to isolate
things from this high opposite candle
and a pullback candle this here is a
valid range so this is the last valid
range that caused the break so you take
it from here okay and pretty much you
keep repeating if if you do that enough
times you are going to master it so
there is our new high from this low to
that high you just wait there is the
market breaking the high so what caused
the break of the high in this case it's
this low because there is nothing else
okay so then we have this higher high
and then the market looks like it's
going to make a trend change there is
the trend change here now looks like
it's going to get a little bit choppy
but just still all systematic there is
the trend change the market is right now
pulling back it formed a valid range low
why is this a valid range low because we
have bearish candles opposite candle
it's it's not a pullback candle though
and then the next candle is a pullback
candle that does not break below this
candle's low and then you just wait for
something to break so right now the very
recent range is this one and you could
potentially right now be looking for
shorts you see how it works and this is
so systematic that we actually built an
indicator to do it exactly for you but
this is only offered inside my private
program but again you can see those are
exactly the same things that we did is
just marked up it probably had some that
I missed
here okay I think I actually missed this
guy here all right but it's actually
going to do it all for you but this is
my personal way to be a systemizing
market structure and it pretty much
works on every single time frame okay
again like you can see here makes the
low opposite candle pullback candle
check that's a valid range Until It
Breaks you ask the question what is the
the valid range that broke the high the
the low there it is breaks up in this
case it should be that one but on the
Fly time frame we're actually using two
pullback candles so that case here we
have an opposite candle pullback candle
but we need one more for the 4AGE but if
I just very quickly go here and I go to
inputs and I say hard time from
calculation and if I do one all right
right now it should move to this low
there it is so now this is the low that
actually caused the break okay so I am
going to wrap it up here it might seem a
little bit confusing but right now I
invite you into our school Community
where we're going to learn a lot more
about this and I also invite you to
start putting in some practice just
learn about the opposite candles just
learn about the pullback candles and you
are actually going to find your own way
around it and if you have any questions
let me know in the comments we can make
an additional video hope it was
insightful let me know and I can't wait
to see you improve your Market structure
and really trade without any doubts at
all